"Do the Side Effects of Ozempic (Semaglutide)
Outweigh the Benefits?"
"Thinner is better,"
is the conventional wisdom
when it comes
to minimizing the risk
of cardiovascular events
like heart attacks and strokes,
but there have been cases
where weight loss medications
actually led to increased
cardiovascular risk
despite significant
reductions in body fat.
So, we can’t just assume
drug-induced weight loss
will help.
Now, if it’s true
that GLP-1 drugs, like Ozempic,
reduce cardiovascular events,
which are some
of our leading causes of death,
then that benefit
would significantly overwhelm
the risk of almost any amount
of thyroid cancer
these drugs may cause.
Let’s look at the data.
Some major trials have found
that among high-risk
individuals with diabetes,
risk of cardiovascular events
were significantly lower
among those
randomized to Ozempic
compared to placebo injections,
but other trials did not.
Interesting how
the lack of benefit was spun
by saying, "Hey,
it’s not inferior to placebo."
But that was the main concern,
that Ozempic, like some
other weight loss drugs,
could actually increase
cardiovascular disease.
So, it was considered a relief
that it had no effect.
Enough evidence
of benefit accrued, though,
that Ozempic
and another GLP-1 drug
were approved
for cardiovascular protection
among individuals
with Type II diabetes.
Remember, these were
originally prescribed
as diabetes drugs.
So, maybe users reduced
their cardiovascular risk
just by lowering
their blood sugars
rather than
by lowering their weight.
What we want to know is this.
What is the effect of Ozempic
on cardiovascular outcomes
in obesity
for people without diabetes?
And, in patients
who have preexisting
cardiovascular disease,
and are overweight or obese,
but do not have diabetes,
those randomized
to weight loss doses of Ozempic
had an overall lower rate
of either having
a cardiovascular event,
like a heart attack or stroke,
or dying from it,
compared to placebo.
That’s exciting,
but we have to highlight
another caveat, though.
The researchers
just looked at
those with preexisting
cardiovascular disease.
That is an important
limitation of these findings.
The effects of these
weight-loss drugs
on the prevention
of cardiovascular events
in those without diagnosed
atherosclerotic disease
have not yet been determined.
Still, a lot
of overweight people
have a history of heart attack,
stroke,
or peripheral vascular disease.
So, how big is the benefit?
Over a period of a few years,
8% of people
with cardiovascular disease
suffered another event
on the placebo,
but only 6.5%
suffered a subsequent event
on the drug.
Going from 8 to 6.5
is a 20% drop.
You can see it clearly
if you zoom in.
Unfortunately,
many news stories focused on
that 20% relative risk reduction
rather than on
the absolute risk reduction
of 1.5%.
Yes, 8 to 6.5 is a 20% drop,
but, at the same time,
you’re really only reducing
your absolute risk by 1.5%.
In other words,
you’d have to treat
67 people with the drug
for a few years
to prevent one heart attack
or stroke
or cardiovascular death.
That may not sound like much
on an individual scale.
I mean, what are the odds
you’re going to be
that 1 in 67th person?
But on a population scale,
it’s huge.
In fact, it’s right up there
with cholesterol-lowering
statin drugs,
which have
an absolute risk reduction
in the same 1.5% ballpark.
So, indeed, in March 2024,
the Food and Drug Administration
approved high-dose Ozempic
for use beyond just weight loss
but also for reducing
cardiovascular risk
in those with
prior cardiovascular disease.
So, how do the benefits
and harms stack up?
In the summer of 2024,
the first quantitative
benefit-harm balance analysis
was published.
The researchers concluded
that for those achieving
a 10% weight loss,
there’s more than a 90% chance
the benefits outweigh the harms,
though the opposite was found
for only a 5% weight loss.
Here’s how they broke it down.
If 1,000 people
go on these GLP-1 drugs,
375 would be expected to lose
at least 10%
of their body weight
with all the ancillary benefits
that would bring.
On the other side
of the equation,
41 people would suffer
from abdominal pain,
57 from hair loss,
8 from gallstones,
118 from constipation,
100 from diarrhea,
22 from dizziness,
84 from an upset stomach,
46 from excessive burping,
39 from fatigue,
51 from excessive farting,
13 from headaches,
17 from low blood sugars,
4 from reactions
at the injection site.
221 would suffer from nausea,
4 from pancreatitis,
43 from upper abdominal pain,
and 110 from vomiting.
Now, of course, the net benefit
versus harm calculation
would be highly dependent on
different people’s willingness
to accept different harms.
Like a bald guy
isn’t going to be concerned
about hair loss, for example.
And this also
doesn’t take into account
the fact that
the benefits peter out.
Weight loss stalls after a year,
but the harms may continue.
So, once
you’ve already plateaued
and stop losing weight,
do you keep taking it
even though you get
no further weight-loss benefit
but the potential for harm
continues to accumulate?
We really don’t know about
the long-term harms or benefits
because some of these drugs
and dosing schedules are so new,
especially now that the American
Academy of Pediatrics
has suggested
offering these drugs
for teens and tweens
as young as age 12.
These drugs work
by acting on the brain,
so, who knows what effect
this could have
on childhood development
and beyond,
if they end up taking them
for the rest of their lives.
In the end,
this story is familiar.
A new class
of antidiabetic agents
is rushed to market
and widely promoted
in the absence
of any evidence
of long-term
beneficial outcomes.
Evidence of harms accumulate,
but it’s vigorously denied
or discounted.
The manufacturers are expected,
quite unrealistically,
to monitor the safety
of their own products.
We should be thankful
that those responsible
for aircraft safety
do not operate
under the same assumption.
Although we now
do have evidence
of at least near-term benefit
over a few years,
we cannot assume
long-term safety
until it has been demonstrated.